Guide to the Joint Center for Political and Economic Studies records, 1966-2014 RL.11552
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Center Offices, 1969-2013
  - Office of Governance and Economic Analysis (OGEA), 1969-2008
    - OGEA Project Administration, 1972-2008
      - OGEA Projects: Economics, 1972-2007
        - Advanced Committee meeting, 2006 Jun 6 (Box 111)
        - National Policy Alliance correspondence, 2006-2007 (Box 111)
        - National Policy Alliance meetings, 2006-2007; 2 folders (Box 111)
        - National Policy Alliance meeting, 2006-2007; 6 folders (Box 111)
        - Regional Equity, 2007; 2 folders (Box 111)
      - OGEA Projects: Employment and workforce training, 1986-2007
        - Transportation Study, 1986 (Box 106)
        - Suggs, Robert - Recent Changes in Black-Owned Business, 1986 Sep (Box 106)
        - Journey to Work Information System, 1986 Nov (Box 106)
        - Woodrow Wilson Program, evaluation of the minority advancement program, 1989 Aug (Box 106)
        - Woodrow Wilson Program report to Ford Foundation, 1989 Oct 1-1991 Jul 31 (Box 106)
        - Woodrow Wilson Program report on participant characteristics, 1989-1992 (Box 106)
        - Woodrow Wilson Program, correspondence, 1989-1995 (Box 106)
        - Rural Poverty, 1990 (Box 106)
        - Woodrow Wilson Program, 1990 cohort mailing (Box 106)
        - Williams, Rhonda M. - Beyond Bad Luck, The Racial Dimensions of Deindustrialization, 1990 Feb; 3 folders (Box 106)
        - Demographic trends/worktrip behavior, 1990-1995; 3 folders (Box 106)
        - Investing in Baltimore, 1991; 2 folders (Box 106)
        - Diversity within American schools, 1991 (Box 106)
        - Youth apprenticeship, 1991-1993 (Box 106)
        - Economic recovery and the economy status of southern black families headed by women, 1991 May (Box 106)
        - Woodrow Wilson Program informational report, 1991 Aug 22 (Box 106)
        - Woodrow Wilson Program evaluation, 1992 Nov (Box 106)
        - Assessment of Government MBDA programs, 1993; 2 folders (Box 106)
        - Minority business development program's assessment of state and local government, 1993 Dec 3 (Box 106)
        - Banking on Black Enterprise, 1993 May (Box 106)
        - Woodrow Wilson Program report on job entry survey, 1993 Sep (Box 106)
        - School-to-work, 1993-1998 (Box 106)
        - Woodrow Wilson Program pairing demonstration program, 1994 Jan (Box 106)
        - Woodrow Wilson Program, impact of the program on graduate school decisions, 1994 Jul (Box 106)
        - Worker training proposal, 1994-1997 (Box 106)
        - Woodrow Wilson Program, synthesis report on program evaluation, 1995 Nov (Box 106)
        - Equitable Transportation Access, 1996-1997; 2 folders (Box 106)
        - Retraining America's Workers, 1996 Nov (Box 106)
        - Employment trends, 1996 Nov 4 (Box 106)
        - Labor force issues, 1996 Dec 31 (Box 107)
        - Black workers project, 1997; 2005 (Box 107)
        - Soft Skills Job Initiative, 1997-2004 (Box 107)
        - Black Americans and Electric Utility Restructuring, 1998-1999 (Box 107)
        - Education and Training for Black Workers, 1998-2000 (Box 107)
        - Scarboro Project, 1999-2001 (Box 107)
        - Bush/Gore Election, 2000 (Box 107)
        - Cultural Competence Job Initiative, 2000-2007 (Box 107)
        - Scarboro Community meeting, 2000 Jan 25; 2 folders (Box 107)
        - Arts engagement, 2001-2003; undated; 4 folders (Box 107)
        - Workforce and Skills Development, Alcoa grant, 2001 Dec 7 (Box 107)
        - Black Men and Boys, 2001-2002; 3 folders (Box 107)
        - Skills Development, 2002 Dec 10 (Box 107)
        - High Tech Job, 2003 Nov 14 (Box 107)
        - Black Worker and Industrialization, 2004 Oct 29 (Box 107)
        - A Mixed Record mailing, 2005 (Box 107)
        - Predatory Mortgage Lending Forum, 2006-2007 (Box 107)
        - More in the Middle, 2007 (Box 107)
        - Workforce Strategic Plan, 2007 (Box 107)
      - OGEA Projects: Political participation, 1975-2000
        This subseries includes Joint Center reports, proposals and papers related to projects and programs designed to increase African American political participation.
        - National Policy Institute, Black Political Participation, 1975 (Box 112)
        - National Policy Institute, How to Encourage Black Political Participation, 1975 (Box 112)
        - Black Suburbanization, 1983 (Box 112)
        - Alternative Service Delivery Systems, 1984; 4 folders (Box 112)
        - Demographic Change, 1984; 2 folders (Box 112)
        - Demographic Change and Recent Worktrip, 1985; 3 folders (Box 112)
        - Urban Drug Abuse Project, 1985-1988 (Box 112)
        - Military Forum, 1985-2008; 35 folders (Box 117)
          Each year the Joint Center hosted an Army War College Fellow in partnership with Army Senior leadership to facilitate research strategic military challenges including racial and ethnic diversity, and career opportunities for women. Files include biographies on the fellows, correspondence, reports, and program agendas, arranged chronologically.
        - Congressional District Factbook, 1986 (Box 112)
        - National Policy Institute, news article, 1987-1991; 5 folders (Box 112)
        - National Policy Institute Steering Committee, 1990 (Box 112)
        - Declining Economic Status of Black Children, 1990 (Box 112)
        - Financial report, 1990 Jul 31 (Box 112)
        - Committee on Policy for Racial Justice, 1990 Sep 28-29; 3 folders (Box 112)
        - Moving Up with Baltimore, 1991 (Box 112)
        - Poverty, Inequality, and the Crisis of Social Policy, 1991 (Box 112)
        - Institutional Development Campaign, 1991 Aug (Box 112)
        - National Center for Research in Vocational Education, 1991 Aug 16 (Box 112)
        - Ford Foundation Refunding Proposal, 1991 Dec (Box 112)
        - Carnegie Corporation of New York, 1991 Jan-Jun (Box 112)
        - Lynde and Harry Bradley Foundation, 1991 Jul (Box 112)
        - Ford Foundation and Aspen Institute, final report, 1991 May (Box 112)
        - Ford Foundation, report, 1991-1992; 2 folders (Box 112)
        - Markle Foundation, proposal, 1991 Oct (Box 112)
        - Rockefeller Foundation, 1991 May (Box 112)
        - William and Flora Hewlett Foundation, 1991 May (Box 112)
        - Sixth National Policy Institute, 1992 (Box 112)
        - Ford Foundation, materials published, 1992 Feb 7 (Box 112)
        - General Electric Foundation, 1992 Apr (Box 112)
        - German Marshall Fund, 1992 Apr (Box 112)
        - Carnegie Corporation of New York, 1992 Jun (Box 112)
        - Biosketches of Mini Town Hall Panelists, 1992 Jun 12 (Box 112)
        - Ford Foundation, report, 1992 May (Box 112)
        - William and Flora Hewlett Foundation, 1992 May (Box 112)
        - Seventh National Policy Institute, 1996 (Box 112)
        - National Policy Institute, FOCUS, 2000 (Box 112)
  - Office of Information Resources (OOR/Library), 1964-2013
    The Joint Center's Office of Information Resources/Library functioned as the organization's resource center and archive, and the subseries includes subject files comprised of Joint Center published and unpublished essays, conference proceedings, studies, and research on policy issues of concern to African American communities. This subseries also includes print materials that range from short pamphlets to books. Most of the materials were printed by the Joint Center. Other materials not printed by the Joint Center include reference books that were used to write reports and pamphlets. Print materials are arranged by topic and include health, voting, education, economics, policy, and Joint Center information. The Joint Center's main publications, Black Elected Officials: A National Roster, and FOCUS magazine, can be found here.The materials did not have a discernible original order and have been grouped by topic and arranged chronologically.
    - OOR Administrative and organization files, 1966-2008
      Includes Joint Center administrative files including correspondence, meeting minutes, reports, transcripts of speeches, media notes, and fact sheets arranged chronologically. Also included are research files and interview transcripts for Walking with Presidents, the biography of Louis Martin, and Darlene C. Hine's research on the history of the Joint Center.
      - Black Executives in NY, NJ, CT, and PA, undated (Box 141)
      - Black Leadership Information Exchange, membership kit, undated (Box 141)
      - Budget Conference fact sheet, undated (Box 146)
      - By-laws, undated (Box 141)
      - Digital Library, undated (Box 141)
      - International Activity, undated (Box 141)
      - JCPES Press, new and recent books, undated (Box 141)
      - Joint Center, fact sheet, undated (Box 141)
      - Joint Center, introduction, undated (Box 146)
      - Joint Center Overview, updated, undated (Box 141)
      - Program director, interview guide, undated (Box 141)
      - Summaries of Articles in Literature Review, undated (Box 141)
      - Transcribed interviews, undated; 3 folders (Box 144)
      - When You Need an Informed Source On..., undated (Box 141)
      - Hine, Darlene C., JCPES history, 1966-1995; 27 folders (Box 41)
        Includes compiled contracts, notes, interviews, references, and proposals related to historian Darlene C. Hine's research and writing on JCPES's history and are arranged chronologically.
      - Louis Martin biography, 1966-2004; undated; 44 folders (Box 51)
        Includes correspondence, research, interview transcripts, contracts, forward, chapters, and biographical materials related to the biography on Louis Martin co-published by the Joint Center, and is arranged chronologically. Also included are interview transcripts with Louis Martin, Gertrude Elizabeth Martin Hatter, Lillian Calhoun, and Charles A. Davis.
      - Claremont College West Coast Service Center, 1970 Nov 30-1971 Apr 7 (Box 141)
      - What is JCPS?, 1973 (Box 141, Box 146)
      - Organization Management Project, 1973 Apr 6 (Box 141)
      - A Proposal to Establish a Public Policy Research Program, 1973 Aug 27 (Box 141)
      - Evaluation of Administrative Organization of Englewood, NJ, 1974 May (Box 144)
      - Personnel directory, 1974 Oct 10 (Box 141)
      - Clark, Kenneth B., materials, 1975-1985 (Box 156)
      - Institute on Management, 1975 Jun 5-7 (Box 144)
      - Office of Program Development board reports, 1976-1997; 4 folders (Box 146)
      - Press kit, 1978 (Box 146)
      - State Financial Management Resource Guide, 1979 Jun (Box 146)
      - Community Services Specialists Training, 1979 Aug 20-31 (Box 146)
      - Certificate of Exemption, 1979; 1983 (Box 146)
      - Board of Governors, retreat, 1980; 1986 (Box 141)
      - JCPS: A Public Policy Research Institution, 1981 Jun (Box 141)
      - Case statement, 1981 Aug (Box 146)
      - Board of Governors, Public Affairs Committee, 1982-1988; 2 folders (Box 141)
      - Sample letters of recommendation, 1982 Jun-1984 Jun (Box 141)
      - Background Information on the Joint Center for Political and Economic Studies, 1983 Nov 22 (Box 141)
      - Joint Center Development Committee, 1984; 1986; 2 folders (Box 141)
      - Associates program, 1984-1991; 3 folders (Box 141)
      - Board of Governors Development Committee, 1984-1991; 2 folders (Box 141)
      - General support proposal, 1984 May 14 (Box 146)
      - JCPS Gallup Survey, 1986 (Box 141)
      - Volunteers, 1986 (Box 146)
      - JCPS Project on International Affairs, 1986-1987 (Box 146)
      - JCPS project report schedule, 1986-1987 (Box 146)
      - Administrative memoranda, 1986-1989 (Box 146)
      - Senior staff meeting and monthly memoranda, 1986-1991 (Box 146)
      - Minority Set-Asides, 1986 Sep 17 (Box 141)
      - Where is the Joint Center Going?, 1986 Nov (Box 141)
      - JCPS Strategic Planning, 1987 (Box 146)
      - JCPS Information Resources, 1987-1991 (Box 146)
      - JCPS Office of Communications, 1987-1992 (Box 146)
      - International Affairs dinner, 1987 Feb 23 (Box 146)
      - Children's Defense Fund, 1987 May 28 (Box 146)
      - Employee survey, 1987 Aug (Box 146)
      - Final Report of the Scholars Clearinghouse, 1987 Oct (Box 141)
      - JCPS formats, 1988; undated (Box 146)
      - Memoranda and minutes, 1988-1989 (Box 146)
      - JCPS Certificate of Registration, 1988 Feb (Box 146)
      - National Forum of Black Public Administrators, 1989-1990 (Box 146)
      - Chadwyck Healey digitizing agreement, 1989-1993 (Box 146)
      - Board of Governors meeting, 1990 Apr 5 (Box 146)
      - Hine, Darlene Clark - Black Politics and Public Policy, 1990 Aug 1 (Box 146)
      - Staff memoranda, 1991 (Box 146)
      - Certificates and commendations, 1991 Jan 11 (Box 146)
      - Document for Board of Governors meeting, 1991 Apr 10 (Box 146)
      - Distinguished Scholars program report, 1991 Nov (Box 146)
      - Gertrude Martin interview transcript, 1991 Dec 1 (Box 41)
      - Louis Martin interview transcript, 1991 Dec 2 (Box 146)
      - HBO/Joint Center poll, 1992 July 8 (Box 141)
      - Williams, Eddie N. - speeches, 1993 (Box 146)
      - Press releases, 1993-1994 (Box 141)
      - Public relations and general information, 1993-1995 (Box 141)
      - Newkirk, Pamela - Louis Martin, biography draft, 1994 (Box 141)
      - HBO screening invitation list, 1994 May 13 (Box 146)
      - Program director, surveys, 1994 Sep 7 (Box 141)
      - A Survey Conducted for JCPES, 1995 May (Box 141)
      - Trademark research, 1995-1999 (Box 141)
      - Finance Committee meeting, 1996 Mar 14 (Box 146)
      - 2030 Center, 1997 (Box 141)
      - Appointments, 1998-2001 (Box 141)
      - Appointments needed, 1998 (Box 141)
      - Ongoing projects, 1998-2003 (Box 141)
      - Copyright permissions, 1999 (Box 141)
      - Board of Governors, correspondence, 2000 (Box 141)
      - Moonlight Cabaret, 2000 (Box 156)
      - Primary Source Tribute to John Hope Franklin, 2000 Jun 17 (Box 146)
      - Allen, William A., 2001 (Box 141)
      - Joint Center media coverage, 2001 (Box 146)
      - Media report, 2004 Jul-Nov 15 (Box 141)
      - Transcripts from Lyndon Baines Johnson Library, Louis Martin biography, 2007 (Box 146)
      - Important Questions: Informed Answers, A Briefing for Funders, 2008 Sep (Box 141)
    - OOR Administrative and Organization magazines, newsletters, reference, 1970-2008
      Includes Joint Center publications, and other reference materials, including magazines, newsletters, newspapers, and other publications. The materials did not have a discernible original order and have been arranged chronologically.
      - Chicago Defender, 1959 Mar 21; 1996 Aug 29; 2 folders (Box 185)
      - Pamphlets, 1970-1978 (Box 185)
      - FOCUS Magazine, 1972 Nov-2011 Dec; 33 folders (Box 135)
      - JCPES History and Facts, 1973-2009; undated; 2 folders (Box 133)
      - JCPES publication catalogs, 1973-1995 (Box 133)
      - JCPES events, 1973-2000 (Box 133)
      - National Black Monitor, 1979 (Box 185)
      - At the Center, 1990 December - 1996 January; 2 folders (Box 135)
      - JCPES speeches, 1993-1997 (Box 133)
      - Michigan Chronicle, 1997 Feb 5-11 (Box 185)
      - JCPES and Harrah's Celebrity Charity Golf Classic invitations, 2003 Nov 1-2 (Box 133)
      - New Media and Community Institute launch paper, 2008 Mar (Box 133)
    - OOR Books, 1969-2011
      Included are books published by the Joint Center for use by government representatives and the general public. Also included are reference books used within the organizations. This subseries is arranged chronologically.
      - National Roster of Black Elected Officials, 1969-1971; 3 folders (Box 134)
      - Johnson, Jesse J. - A Pictorial History of Black Soldiers in the United States, 1619-1969, 1970 (Box 121)
      - National Roster of Black Elected Officials, Supplement, 1972 Mar (Box 134)
      - National Roster of Black Elected Officials, 1973-1982; 10 folders (Box 134)
      - Bryce, Herrington J. - Small Cities in Transition: The Dynamics of Growth and Decline, 1977 (Box 121)
      - Directory of Black State Legislators, 1977 (Box 134)
      - Profiles of Black Mayors in America, 1977 (Box 121)
      - Directory of Black Elected Women Officials, 1983 (Box 134)
      - Black Elected Officials: A National Roster, 1984 (Box 134)
      - Davidson, Chandler - Minority Vote Dilution, 1984 (Box 121)
      - Black Elected Officials: A National Roster, 1985-1991; 1993; 8 folders (Box 124)
      - Carson, Emmett D. - The Charitable Appeal Fact Book: How Black and White Americans Respond to Different Types of Fund-raising Efforts, 1989 (Box 124)
      - Suggs, Robert E. - Minorities and Privatization: Economic Mobility at Risk, 1989 (Box 124)
      - Who Defends America: Race, Sex, and Class in the Armed Services, 1989 (Box 121)
      - Parker, Frank R. - Black Votes Count: Political Empowerment in Mississippi after 1965, 1990 (Box 121)
      - Ragsdale, Bruce A. and Joel D. Treese - Black Americans in Congress, 1870-1989, 1990 (Box 121)
      - Arrington, Karen McGill, and William L. Taylor - Voting Rights in America: Continuing the Quest for Full Participation, 1992 (Box 121)
      - Bates, Timothy - Majority Studies of Minority Business: A Bibliographic Review, 1993 (Box 124)
      - Bostis, David A. - The Congressional Black Caucus in the 103rd Congress, 1994 (Box 124)
      - Directory of Minority Judges in the United States, 1994 (Box 121)
      - Rexroat, Cynthia - The Declining Economic Status of Black Children, 1994 (Box 124)
      - Jackson, Barbara L. - Balancing Act: The Political Role of the Urban School Superintendent, 1995 (Box 121)
      - Achieving Equitable Access: Studies of Health Care Issues Affecting Hispanics and African Americans, 1996 (Box 121)
      - Wyatt, Gail Elizabeth, Dr. - Stolen Women: Reclaiming our Sexuality, Taking Back Our Lives, 1997 (Box 121)
      - Bostis, David A. - Redistricting and Minority Representation: Learning from the Past, Preparing for the Future, 1998 (Box 121)
      - Leigh, Wilhemina A., and Margaret C. Simms - The Black Worker in the 21st Century, Volume 1: Job Creation, 1998 (Box 124)
      - Simms, Margaret C. - Black Economic Progress: An Agenda for the 1990s, 1998 (Box 121)
      - Smith, Jessie Carney and Joseph M. Palmisano - The African American Almanac, 2000 (Box 121)
      - National Directory of African American Organizations, 2001-2003 (Box 121)
      - Austin, Algernon - Getting it Wrong: How Black Public Intellectuals are Failing Black America, 2006 (Box 121)
      - Conrad, Cecilia A. - The Black Worker in the 21st Century, Volume 2: Building Skills for Black Workers, 2004 (Box 124)
      - Legacy of Leadership, 2011 (Box 121)
    - OOR Subject files, 1972-2013
      The subseries includes subject groups with files comprised of Joint Center published and unpublished essays, conference proceedings, studies, and research. Most topics in this subseries also contain printed materials, including pamphlets and brochures, that address policy issues. These materials did not have a discernible original order and have been arranged chronologically by topic.
      - OOR Economics, files, 1972-2009
        Subject files contain materials related to minority business, employment and economic opportunity, as published and unpublished essays, conference proceedings, studies, and research arranged chronologically.
        - Anheuser-Busch, undated (Box 154)
        - Charitable Activities of Black Americans, undated (Box 139)
        - Economic Perspectives on Affirmative Action, undated (Box 139)
        - O'Hare, W. P. - Analyzing the Difference in Poverty Estimates, undated (Box 139)
        - Poor Support for Children, undated (Box 139)
        - Poverty, Inequality and the Crisis of Social Conference Papers Policy, undated (Box 139)
        - Problems of Small Cities, undated (Box 139)
        - Rose, Ruth - Lone Parents, undated (Box 154)
        - Survey on nonprofits and welfare, undated (Box 139)
        - Work Requirements under the New Welfare Block Grant, undated (Box 139)
        - White House Small Towns Project, 1972 (Box 139)
        - Community Economic Development Seminar, 1973 Feb 24 (Box 139)
        - HUD Workshop, 1974-1975 (Box 139)
        - Conference on City Budgets and Human Need, 1974 Apr 20 (Box 145)
        - 1970 Census Undercount and Revenue Sharing, 1974 Jun (Box 145)
        - Local governmental finance, 1975 (Box 145)
        - Farrar, Eleanor - A Possible Reality Aborted, 1975 Jun (Box 139)
        - Institute on Management, 1975 Feb 20-22 (Box 139)
        - Local Government Finance and Budgeting Institutes, 1975 Apr (Box 139)
        - Brimmer, Andrew F. - The National Economy and the Black Community, 1975 Oct 10 (Box 139)
        - Bryce, Herrington J. - Employment Strategies for the Future, 1975 Dec (Box 139)
        - Techniques of Coalition Building by Sautter, Carl, 1975 Dec (Box 145)
        - City, County Officials Learn Financing, 1977 Jul 2 (Box 139)
        - Rising Energy Prices and the Future of Urban America, 1978 (Box 139)
        - Energy and Jobs by Rodberg, Leonard S., 1978 Jun (Box 145)
        - Training Institute on Public Finance, Budgeting and Management, 1979 Mar 15-17; 2 folders (Box 145)
        - Joint Center presentation to Secretary of Housing and Urban Development, 1980 Mar 20 (Box 145)
        - Equity Versus Efficiency in Human Capital Development, 1982 (Box 139)
        - Seminar on International Trade, 1982 (Box 145)
        - Publications on economics, 1982-1983; 2001 (Box 145)
        - Bryce, Herrington - Blacks and Jobs in Changing America, 1982 Sep (Box 139)
        - Blacks, Demographic Change and Public Policy, 1982 Sep 16-17 (Box 139)
        - Felder, Henry E. - Executive Summary of the Economic Status of Black Americans, 1982 Oct (Box 139)
        - Recent Black Suburbanization in the South by O'Hare, William P., 1982 Oct 6-8 (Box 145)
        - Black Business Enterprise, 1983 Mar (Box 139)
        - Industrial Policy and Minority Economic Opportunity, 1983 May 10 (Box 145)
        - Industrial Policy and Economic Opportunity, 1983 May 10 (Box 139)
        - Dorn, Edwin - Education, Equal Opportunity, and Military Service, 1983 Jun 3 (Box 139)
        - Analyzing the Difference in Poverty, 1983 Oct (Box 139)
        - Hearing the Recent Increase in the Poverty Rate, 1983 Oct 18 (Box 139)
        - Cavanagh, Thomas E. - The Meaning of the 1984 Election, 1984 Dec 4 (Box 139)
        - Natural Gas Consumption in Poverty Households, 1985 Feb (Box 139)
        - Trends, Prospects, and Strategies for Black Economic Progress, 1985 Mar (Box 145)
        - Alternative Service Delivery Systems, report, 1985 Apr (Box 139)
        - Background materials for Wingspread conference, 1985 Apr 4-6 (Box 145)
        - Squires, Gregory - Equity, Employment, and Private Investment, 1985 Oct (Box 139)
        - Privatization and Social Welfare, 1986 Mar (Box 145)
        - The Best Metros for Blacks, 1986 Jul (Box 139)
        - Factors Affecting the Earnings and Welfare Income of Unmarried Mothers, 1986 Aug (Box 145)
        - Suggs, Robert - Executive Summary, 1986 Sep (Box 139)
        - Suggs, Robert - Executive Summary of Recent Changes in Black-Owned Business, 1986 Sep (Box 139)
        - Minority Set-Asides, 1986 Sep 17 (Box 139)
        - National Corporation for Housing Partnerships, 1987-1988 (Box 145)
        - Japan, 1987-1988 (Box 145)
        - Views on the Underclass, 1987 Mar 5; 2 folders (Box 145)
        - Black Philanthropic Activity, 1987 Mar 18 (Box 139)
        - Government Procurement and Minority Business Development, 1987 May 21 (Box 139)
        - Carson, Emmett D. Black Philanthropic Activity, Past and Present, 1987 Jun 15 (Box 139)